Hey guys, welcome back to our IELTS Listening course.
In the previous lesson, we learned how to
do multiple choice questions.
In today's lesson, we'll continue practicing listening skills
with pick from a list of questions or
multiple choice questions with more than one correct answer.
Candidates can be easily tricked when they're given
a long list of possible answers, typically ranging
from four to five choices.
Therefore, we should be highly focused when doing the test.
Today's lesson is divided into three parts.
Part 1. General introduction to pick from a list of questions.
Part 2. Strategy or steps to handle the question type.
And part 3. Practice and explanation.
Let's come to the first part, general introduction
to pick from a list of questions.
In pick from a list of question types,
you are given a longer list of possible answers
and required to choose more than one
correct answer for each pair of questions.
Normally, there are two or three correct answers.
In a pick from a list of questions,
you can hear students and their teachers discuss
classroom work, group assignments, or projects.
This question type usually appears in section two
or three of the IELTS Listening test.
Now, let's move on to part 2.
Strategy or steps to handle the question type.
Let's take a look at this question.
For this question type, here's what we're going to do.
Step one, read the instructions carefully to note
the number of correct answers you need to find.
For today's listening test, you're required to choose
two correct answers for each question.
Step two, underline keywords.
In step two, we need to underline keywords
in the questions and options.
A key thing to remember, just because you
hear the keywords of an option in the recording
doesn't mean it's the correct answer.
Speakers often mention only certain keywords
of an option to trick candidates into thinking
it's the correct answer.
So be extra careful when answering this question.
Let's see what keywords these questions contain.
For the first pair of questions, the keywords
are reasons, learning a language, identify, and most common.
In the options, the keywords are
A, foreign films
B, career prospects
C, please parents
D, traveling easier
E, foreign music.
For the second pair of questions, 23 and 24,
the keywords are things, find, most difficult,
and learning a language.
In the options, the keywords are
A, fast speech
B, complex grammar
C, remembering new vocabulary
D, pronunciation
E, writing essays
For the third pair of questions, the keywords
are learning tools, most popular, and students, surveyed.
In the options, the keywords are
A, textbooks
B, movies
C, television series
D, exchange apps
E, dictionaries.
For the final pair of questions, 27 and 28.
the keywords are tasks, Leo and Mia,
agree, and next.
In the options, the keywords are
A, write a report
B, interview a teacher
C, record a video
D, buy books
E, create a poster.
Step three, listen to the recording
and choose the correct answers.
The first important thing you should remember is
that the options might not come in order
as the information in the recording, which can
easily lead to confusion.
So, we need to remember as many options as possible.
Secondly, keep in mind that the speaker might
use words similar to the ones in the options,
which could be a distraction.
So watch out for such cases.
Finally, the options can come in the form
of synonyms or paraphrases.
For example, instead of food, we can hear
the word dishes.
So, mastering synonyms is crucial for success in
the IELTS Listening test, especially when dealing with
this type of question.
Step four, choose and write the correct answers.
Many candidates can make a mistake
when writing the answers.
It's crucial to remember that
for this question type, you don't write out the whole answer.
Instead, you only select two letters corresponding to
two correct answers.
Let's choose the correct answers to these questions.
Part three, you will hear two university students,
Bob and Mia, discussing a research project for
their language and communication module.
First, you have some time to look at
questions 21 to 28.
Now, listen and answer questions 21 to 28.
Hi Mia, thanks for meeting me.
We really need to catch up on our
research project for the language and communication module.
How is the data analysis going?
It's going well, but it's a lot of work.
I've been looking at the survey results all morning.
How's the first draft of our paper coming along?
It's okay.
I've actually just finished writing the introduction, and
in the next part, we need to explain
our main focus, the reasons why university students
today choose to learn a second language.
Great!
From my interviews, the most common reason was
definitely for future careers.
Most students feel that being bilingual is essential
to secure a good job these days.
I found that too.
I also noticed that many people are motivated
by travel.
Many now solo travel across countries, and they
want to be able to talk to locals on their own,
not just stay in tourist areas
or depend on tour guides.
Yeah, and I expected many would say they
do it because of their parents' wants, but
that wasn't a very common answer in my group.
It's a good thing to learn that their motivation
for language learning comes from inside, not outside.
And surprisingly, very few said they chose a
language just because they liked the music or
films from that country.
Actually, it's quite predictable for me.
Anyway, we also need to discuss
the hardest parts of the learning process.
Most students said that while their pronunciation isn't perfect,
they don't really worry about it
as long as people understand them.
Yeah, because they only consider language
as a tool for communication.
What really makes students struggle is the speed
of natural speech.
When you hear native speakers talking to each other,
it's so hard to follow.
Agree.
And it was a bit of a surprise
when people said they find learning vocabulary
much more frustrating than learning grammar rules.
Actually, it's quite logical once you study them.
There are just so many words to memorize.
Now, let's look at what actually helps students
in their language learning journey.
Many of them complain that textbooks are usually
boring and do not provide much help.
Instead, they highly recommended using language exchange apps
to text or voice call someone in another country.
I also realized that they prefer
to exchange language with someone their own age.
Another popular method was watching television series
in the target language.
They said it's better than movies
because you get used to the same characters' voices
over many episodes.
I also tried suggesting dictionaries, but most students
said those felt a bit old-fashioned and not effective.
Yeah.
So, what should we do next for our presentation?
We have all our data now.
Well, our professor said we should get a
professional opinion.
How about we interview Professor Duncan
from the language department?
That's a great idea.
He can give us a different perspective.
Oh, and let's conduct the interview face-to-face
so we don't need to video it.
That's okay.
I will email the professor soon
to make sure he can have some time for us.
Hmm.
We don't need more books, right?
That's right.
I think we have been provided enough sources
for the research, but we need to think
about how to show our results.
Instead of just a long report,
why don't we design a large poster?
We can put all our graphs and charts on it
so it's easy for the class to see.
That sounds perfect.
That is the end of part three.
You now have half a minute to check
your answers to part three.
Time's up.
Let's check the answers with me.
Hi, Mia.
Thanks for meeting me.
We really need to catch up on our
research project for the language and communication module.
How is the data analysis going?
It's going well, but it's a lot of work.
I've been looking at the survey results all morning.
How's the first draft of our paper coming along?
It's okay.
I've actually just finished writing the introduction, and
in the next part we need to explain
our main focus, the reasons why university students
today choose to learn a second language.
Great.
From my interviews, the most common reason was
definitely for future careers.
Most students feel that being bilingual is essential
to secure a good job these days.
I found that too.
I also noticed that many people are motivated
by travel.
Many now solo travel across countries,
and they want to be able to talk to locals on their own,
not just stay in tourist areas or depend on tour guides.
Yeah, and I expected many would say they
do it because of their parents' wants, but
that wasn't a very common answer in my
It's a good thing to learn that
their motivation for language learning comes from inside,
not outside.
And, surprisingly, very few said they chose a
language just because they liked the music or
films from that country.
Take a look at question 21 and 22.
Let's pay attention to the discussion on reasons.
Mia mentions that the most common reason was
for future careers, and specifically says students feel
it is essential to secure a good job.
This matches option B, to improve career prospects.
Then, Bob adds that many people are motivated
by travel and want to talk to locals
on their own.
This matches option D, to make traveling easier.
Notice that Mia mentions parents' wants, but she
explicitly says that wasn't a very common answer,
so we eliminate C.
Bob also mentions music or films, but notes
that very few chose that reason, so we
eliminate A and E.
So the answers are B and D.
Actually, it's quite predictable for me.
Anyway, we also need to discuss the hardest
parts of the learning process.
Most students said that while their pronunciation isn't perfect,
they don't really worry about it,
as long as people understand them.
Yeah, because they only consider language
as a tool for communication.
What really makes students struggle is the speed
of natural speech.
When you hear native speakers talking to each other,
it's so hard to follow.
Agree.
And it was a bit of a surprise
when people said they find learning vocabulary much more
frustrating than learning grammar rules.
Actually, it's quite logical once you study them.
There are just so many words to memorize.
Now let's turn to the next set of questions.
Here, the speakers discuss the hardest parts.
Bob mentions pronunciation, but he says students don't
really worry about it, so D is incorrect.
Then, Mia states that what makes students struggle
is the speed of natural speech, and that
native speakers are hard to follow.
This corresponds to A, understanding fast speech.
Next, Bob notes that students find learning vocabulary
much more frustrating than learning grammar rules.
Since they find vocabulary harder,
C, remembering new vocabulary,
is the correct answer.
And we can eliminate B, so the answers
are A and C.
Now, let's look at what actually helps students
in their language learning journey.
Many of them complain that textbooks are usually
boring and do not provide much help.
Instead, they highly recommended using language exchange apps
to text or voice call someone in another country.
I also realized that they prefer to exchange language
with someone their own age.
Another popular method was watching television series
in the target language.
They said it's better than movies because you
get used to the same characters' voices over
many episodes.
I also tried suggesting dictionaries, but most students
said those felt a bit old-fashioned and not effective.
Up next are questions 25 and 26.
Bob mentions that students complain about textbooks, so
A is wrong.
However, he says they highly recommended
using language exchange apps.
This points us to D, language exchange apps.
Mia adds that another popular method
was watching television series.
She explicitly compares this to movies, stating students
said TV series are better than movies.
This means C is correct and B is incorrect.
Finally, Bob mentions dictionaries were considered old-fashioned
and not effective, ruling out E,
so the answers are C and D.
Yeah, so what should we do next for our presentation?
We have all our data now.
Well, our professor said we should get a professional opinion.
How about we interview Professor Duncan
from the language department?
That's a great idea.
He can give us a different perspective.
Oh, and let's conduct the interview face-to-face
so we don't need to video it.
That's okay.
I will email the professor soon to make
sure he can have some time for us.
Hmm, we don't need more books, right?
That's right.
I think we have been provided enough sources
for the research.
But we need to think about how to
show our results.
Instead of just a long report, why don't
we design a large poster?
We can put all our graphs and charts
on it so it's easy for the class to see.
That sounds perfect.
Last but not least, let's look at 27 and 28.
Bob suggests they interview Professor Duncan.
Mia agrees, saying that's a great idea.
This matches B, interview a language teacher.
Mia suggests doing it face-to-face so
they don't need to video it, so C is incorrect.
Bob confirms they don't need more books, eliminating D.
Finally, Bob suggests that instead of just a
long report, they should design a large poster.
And Mia thinks that sounds perfect.
This matches E, create a visual poster.
So the answers are B and E.
So, how many correct answers have you got?
I believe with frequent practice,
this will no longer be challenging anymore.
Now, let's review what we've learned.
Today's lesson was divided into three parts.
Part 1. General introduction to pick from a list of questions.
Part 2. Strategy or steps to handle the question type.
And Part 3. Practice and explanation.
Also, please memorize some notes for this question type.
First, speakers often mention only certain keywords
as an option to trick candidates into thinking
it's the correct answer.
Secondly, you should read the instructions carefully to
note the way of writing the answers.
Alright, that's it for today's lesson.
Don't forget to do the exercises and practice
what you've learned regularly.
Goodbye and see you in the next lesson.